Hello, I'm here to talk about Project Loom.
안녕하세요, 프로젝트 룸에 대해 이야기하러 왔습니다.
Can I just get a quick show of hands who's actually tried virtual threads already?
가상 실을 사용해 보신 분들 손 좀 들어주실래요?
Okay, maybe about a third of the people.
좋아요, 아마 1/3 정도일 거예요.
Okay, thanks very much.
좋아요, 감사합니다.
Just wanted to get an idea.
그냥 아이디어를 얻고 싶었어요.
Okay, so Project Loom, what's it about?
좋아, 그럼 프로젝트 룸은 뭐지?
So Project Loom is a project in OpenJDK that's really about upgrading the Java concurrency
프로젝트 룸은 Java 동시성을 업그레이드하는 OpenJDK의 프로젝트입니다.
model.
모델입니다.
It's all about high-scale server applications.
대규모 서버 애플리케이션에 관한 모든 것입니다.
So there's a lot of concurrency and a great story for concurrency in the Java platform
따라서 Java 플랫폼에는 많은 동시성과 동시성에 대한 훌륭한 스토리가 있습니다.
right from all the way back to JDK 1.
JDK 1까지 거슬러 올라갑니다.
First-class support for Java monitors.
Java 모니터에 대한 최고 수준의 지원.
Since Java 5, there's a Java 2 concurrency, concurrent APIs for more advanced concurrency
Java 5부터 Java 2 동시성, 고급 동시성을 위한 동시 API가 있습니다.
features.
기능이 추가되었습니다.
And so this is all good.
이제 모두 정상입니다.
But what Project Loom, at least initially, is focusing on concurrency, which is about
하지만 적어도 초기에 프로젝트 룸은 동시성에 초점을 맞추고 있습니다.
thread per request or thread per task or thread per connection, which is very much the traditional
요청당 스레드 또는 작업당 스레드 또는 연결당 스레드, 이는 매우 전통적인
thread per task scheduling model.
작업당 스레드입니다.
This is something that we all know and like, because it's very simple to work with, but
이것은 작업하기가 매우 간단하기 때문에 우리 모두가 알고 있고 좋아하는 것입니다.
it really only tops out with a few thousand concurrent tasks when you're actually mapping
실제로 매핑을 할 때는 수천 개의 동시 작업으로만 정점을 찍습니다.
those tasks to an operating system or, since JDK 19, what we call a platform thread.
이러한 작업을 운영 체제 또는 JDK 19부터는 플랫폼 스레드라고 부르는 것에 매핑합니다.
What we think with Project Loom and with virtual threads is that we can actually scale this
프로젝트 룸과 가상 스레드를 사용하면 실제로 다음과 같이 확장할 수 있다고 생각합니다.
model a lot further.
모델을 훨씬 더 확장할 수 있습니다.
Some other languages and runtimes have done this kind of thing as well.
다른 언어와 런타임에서도 이런 종류의 작업을 수행했습니다.
So instead of topping out at a couple of few thousand concurrent tasks, we should be able
따라서 몇 천 개의 동시 작업에서 정점을 찍는 대신 다음과 같이 할 수 있어야 합니다.
to scale up to have a couple of hundred thousand tasks, concurrent tasks, or even millions
수십만 개의 작업, 동시 작업 또는 수백만 개의 작업으로 확장할 수 있어야 합니다.
of concurrent tasks.
동시 작업의 수입니다.
So what we've done is expose this thing called virtual threads, and they're exposed to developers
그래서 우리가 한 일은 가상 스레드라는 것을 노출한 것이고, 개발자에게 노출된 것입니다.
with the Java API.
자바 API로.
So the old API that we've actually been there since JDK 1.0, but cleaned up, some of the
따라서 JDK 1.0부터 실제로 존재했지만 정리된 이전 API 중 일부인
baggage is gone, but with a much more scalable implementation.
수하물은 사라졌지만 훨씬 더 확장 가능한 구현으로 바뀌었습니다.
The big advantage of this is that we can continue with very sequential blocking code that's
이 방법의 가장 큰 장점은 다음과 같은 매우 순차적인 차단 코드를 계속 사용할 수 있다는 것입니다.
very, very easy to read and write, and it also has very understandable control flow.
읽기 및 쓰기가 매우 쉽고 제어 흐름도 매우 이해하기 쉽습니다.
And understandable control flow is really important when actually maintaining code.
실제로 코드를 유지 관리할 때 이해하기 쉬운 제어 흐름은 정말 중요합니다.
The alternative to this is what some, at least advanced developers, have been doing for the
이에 대한 대안으로 일부, 적어도 고급 개발자들은
last while is, because things were topping out at a couple of thousand concurrent threads,
에 대한 대안은 동시 스레드 수가 수천 개에 달했기 때문입니다,
is they've been making use of the async and reactive type APIs.
비동기 및 반응형 API를 사용하고 있다는 것입니다.
That leads to very contorted code in some cases.
이로 인해 경우에 따라 매우 왜곡된 코드가 생성됩니다.
It might be okay to read, it might look okay, but it's very, very hard code to maintain,
읽기에는 괜찮고 보기에는 괜찮을지 모르지만 유지 관리하기에는 매우 어려운 코드입니다,
debug, profile, and so on.
디버그, 프로파일 등.
Things like stack traces and stuff don't always make sense in those kind of environments.
스택 추적과 같은 것들이 이런 환경에서는 항상 의미가 있는 것은 아닙니다.
There's a couple of other aspects to Project Loom, and I'm going to talk a little bit about
프로젝트 룸에는 몇 가지 다른 측면이 있는데, 그 중 몇 가지에 대해 조금 이야기해볼게요.
this today, particularly around grouping of tasks that are part of some larger unit of
특히 더 큰 단위의 일부인 작업 그룹화에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
work.
작업.
So, virtual threads, as I said, are just a different implementation of threading.
따라서 가상 스레드는 앞서 말했듯이 스레딩의 다른 구현일 뿐입니다.
So, rather than being tied to an operating system thread and carrying around this big
따라서 운영 체제 스레드에 묶여 이 큰 파일을 가지고 다니는 대신
continuous stack, virtual threads work a little bit differently in that they're managed by
연속 스택을 가지고 다니는 대신, 가상 스레드는 다음과 같이 관리된다는 점에서 약간 다르게 작동합니다.
the Java runtime.
에 의해 관리됩니다.
The thread stack is actually a sort of a pay-as-you-go stack that's actually stored in the Java heap.
스레드 스택은 실제로 Java 힙에 저장되는 일종의 종량제 스택입니다.
It makes use of some lower level constructs in the VM to be able to support this.
이를 지원하기 위해 VM의 일부 하위 수준 구성을 사용합니다.
And what it means is that we can have a lot more virtual threads than we can have platform
그리고 이것이 의미하는 바는 플랫폼보다 훨씬 더 많은 가상 스레드를 가질 수 있다는 것입니다.
threads.
스레드.
If you've ever seen any diagrams of different threading models, what we have is kind of
다른 스레딩 모델에 대한 다이어그램을 본 적이 있다면, 우리가 가진 것은 일종의
closer to what we call an end-to-end model, where you've got n virtual threads, let's
n개의 가상 스레드가 있는 엔드투엔드 모델에 더 가깝다고 할 수 있습니다.
say a million virtual threads, and they sit on top of, are carried by n platform threads,
백만 개의 가상 스레드가 있고, 그 위에 플랫폼 스레드 n개가 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다,
or operating system threads.
또는 운영 체제 스레드에 의해 수행됩니다.
And we refer to these threads that are managed by a scheduler in the Java runtime, we refer
그리고 Java 런타임에서 스케줄러에 의해 관리되는 이러한 스레드를 참조합니다.
to those as carrier threads when they're in use.
를 사용 중일 때 캐리어 스레드라고 합니다.
So I said about that we use a Java thread API.
Java 스레드 API를 사용한다고 말씀드렸습니다.
One of the things is we spent over five years working on Project Loom.
프로젝트 룸을 개발하는 데 5년이 넘게 걸렸습니다.
Project Loom was very much a jack up the houses, replace the foundations, and put the house
프로젝트 룸은 집을 들어 올리고, 기초를 교체하고, 집을 짓는 작업이었어요.
down without actually breaking anything type of feature.
어떤 기능도 실제로 파괴하지 않고 무너뜨렸습니다.
And the API surface that it actually exposes is tiny.
그리고 실제로 노출되는 API 표면은 아주 작습니다.
There's some upgrades to the Java Lang thread API, there's some new factory methods on Java
Java Lang 스레드 API에 몇 가지 업그레이드가 있었고, Java에 몇 가지 새로운 팩토리 메서드가 있습니다.
util concurrent executors, and that's about it for the developer facing APIs.
동시 실행자 활용, 그리고 개발자가 API를 대면하는 데는 여기까지입니다.
There's a whole bunch of other stuff that is interesting for tools, debuggers, troubleshooting
도구, 디버거, 문제 해결에 흥미로운 다른 많은 것들이 있습니다.
type of APIs, where there's more surface there.
더 많은 표면이 있는 API 유형.
But for this talk, I'm not going to talk too much about that.
하지만 이번 강연에서는 이에 대해 너무 많이 이야기하지 않겠습니다.
But just to say is that this is a whole platform type of feature.
다만 말씀드리고 싶은 것은 이것이 전체 플랫폼 유형의 기능이라는 것입니다.
Although the developer facing APIs are tiny, reimplementing threads basically required
개발자 대면 API는 작지만 기본적으로 스레드 재구현이 필요합니다.
revisiting almost every area of the platform.
플랫폼의 거의 모든 영역을 재검토해야 했습니다.
Okay, so I just want to show just a couple of examples just to actually to show you using
자, 이제 몇 가지 예시를 보여드리겠습니다.
virtual threads.
가상 스레드.
What I've got here is a piece of code that makes a connection to oracle.com, downloads
여기에는 오라클닷컴에 연결하고, 다운로드하는 코드 조각이 있습니다.
the index.html file as a page and copies it to a local file.
index.html 파일을 페이지로 만들고 로컬 파일에 복사합니다.
This is boring code.
지루한 코드입니다.
This is really, really boring code.
정말, 정말 지루한 코드입니다.
And that's really what the point of this is.
이게 바로 이 코드의 요점입니다.
There's nothing new here.
여기엔 새로운 게 없어요.
This is code that you've probably seen 100 times.
아마 100번은 봤을 코드입니다.
This is code that's using the old synchronous IO APIs.
이전 동기 IO API를 사용하는 코드입니다.
But the interesting thing is that it's not consuming, it's an operating system thread
하지만 흥미로운 점은 이것이 소비하는 것이 아니라 운영 체제 스레드라는 것입니다.
for the entire duration of this code.
이 코드의 전체 기간 동안.
When it's blocking to actually do something, then it can actually return that operating
실제로 무언가를 수행하는 것을 차단하는 경우 실제로 해당 작동을 반환할 수 있습니다.
system thread back to the runtime and allow that operating system thread to be used to
시스템 스레드를 런타임으로 되돌리고 해당 운영 체제 스레드를 사용할 수 있도록 허용합니다.
do other work.
다른 작업을 수행합니다.
So that's the interesting thing about this example.
이것이 이 예제의 흥미로운 점입니다.
Now when you look at this example, there's a lot of actually blocking IO, a lot of blocking
이제 이 예제를 보면 실제로 차단하는 IO가 많고, 차단하는 것이 많습니다.
going on here.
계속되고 있습니다.
I do a DNS lookup of oracle.com.
oracle.com의 DNS 조회를 수행합니다.
I'm going to make a connection to its HTTP connection.
HTTP 연결에 연결합니다.
It's actually HTTPS.
실제로는 HTTPS입니다.
So in addition to making a TCP connection, I'm going to have this little chatter where
따라서 TCP 연결을 만드는 것 외에도 다음과 같은 작은 잡담을 할 것입니다.
I'm going to talk SSL to and negotiate with the server on the other end.
상대방 서버와 SSL로 대화하고 협상할 것입니다.
There's a lot of blocking actually going on here.
실제로 많은 차단이 진행되고 있습니다.
And when I start reading the page from, I'm doing a lot of blocking IO.
그리고 내가 페이지를 읽기 시작할 때, 나는 많은 차단 IO를 하고 있습니다.
And this is all code that is interesting for virtual threads because it can be implemented
그리고 이것은 모두 가상 스레드에서 구현할 수 있기 때문에 흥미로운 코드입니다.
very, very efficiently.
매우, 매우 효율적으로 구현할 수 있기 때문입니다.
Now in terms of APIs here, the only new API being used here is just a factory method on
이제 API 측면에서 볼 때, 여기서 사용되는 유일한 새로운 API는 단지
Java Lang thread, which starts a virtual thread.
가상 스레드를 시작하는 Java Lang 스레드입니다.
That's all it did.
여기까지입니다.
You give it a task in the form of a runnable.
실행 가능한 형태의 태스크를 제공합니다.
It starts a virtual thread to run that task.
해당 태스크를 실행하기 위해 가상 스레드를 시작합니다.
That's it.
끝입니다.
Nothing too interesting.
별로 흥미로운 건 없습니다.
That factory method is actually shorthand for what the code I've showed here, which
이 팩토리 메서드는 사실 제가 여기서 보여드린 코드의 줄임말입니다.
is using thread of builder and then a start method.
은 빌더의 스레드를 사용한 다음 시작 메서드를 사용하고 있습니다.
What we have here is a new builder API for creating threads.
여기에는 스레드 생성을 위한 새로운 빌더 API가 있습니다.
This allows you to wait to start threads.
이를 통해 스레드 시작을 기다릴 수 있습니다.
You can set properties of the thread, like its thread name.
스레드 이름과 같은 스레드의 속성을 설정할 수 있습니다.
There's also interesting methods in there for creating unstarted threads or creating
시작되지 않은 스레드를 생성하거나 다음과 같은 흥미로운 방법도 있습니다.
a thread factory.
스레드 공장.
That makes migration very, very easy and makes it easy to integrate code with new code using
이렇게 하면 마이그레이션이 매우 쉬워지고 다음을 사용하여 코드를 새 코드와 쉽게 통합할 수 있습니다.
virtual threads and existing code that uses thread factories and so on.
가상 스레드 및 스레드 팩토리 등을 사용하는 기존 코드와 쉽게 통합할 수 있습니다.
Now, the only other API then is, as you may have heard of, Executor Service.
이제 다른 유일한 API는 여러분도 들어보셨겠지만 Executor 서비스입니다.
That's the interface that's actually used for things like thread pools in Java, Util
이것은 실제로 Java의 스레드 풀과 같은 것들에 사용되는 인터페이스입니다.
Concurrent.
동시성.
Thread pools are about reusing a set of threads to execute tasks.
스레드 풀은 스레드 집합을 재사용하여 작업을 실행하는 것입니다.
But the Executor Service interface can be actually re-implemented with other policies.
그러나 실행자 서비스 인터페이스는 실제로 다른 정책으로 다시 구현할 수 있습니다.
We have a very simple implementation of Executor Service.
실행자 서비스를 매우 간단하게 구현했습니다.
It implements the policy of creating a virtual thread for every task.
모든 작업에 대해 가상 스레드를 생성하는 정책을 구현합니다.
Virtual threads are so cheap, we can actually create a virtual thread for every task.
가상 스레드는 매우 저렴하기 때문에 실제로 모든 작업에 대해 가상 스레드를 생성할 수 있습니다.
That's the whole point.
그게 요점입니다.
Virtual threads were a preview feature in Java 19 and 20.
가상 스레드는 Java 19와 20의 미리보기 기능입니다.
There was a lot of articles written about it.
이에 대한 많은 기사가 작성되었습니다.
It actually created quite a lot of buzz.
실제로 꽤 많은 화제를 불러일으켰죠.
In fact, at one point, we actually even had a Wikipedia page called Virtual Threads.
사실 한때는 가상 스레드라는 위키피디아 페이지가 있을 정도였죠.
I should say this is to credit Brian Goetz for coming up with the term virtual threads.
가상 스레드라는 용어를 생각해낸 브라이언 괴츠에게 감사의 말을 전하고 싶네요.
We had tried different names in all the different prototypes and things, but he correctly compared
우리는 모든 다른 프로토타입과 물건에서 다른 이름을 시도했지만 그는 정확하게 비교했습니다.
it to virtual memory and memory management systems.
가상 메모리와 메모리 관리 시스템으로 바꿨어요.
So the term virtual thread was born.
그래서 가상 스레드라는 용어가 탄생했습니다.
Now, since, by the way, this Wikipedia page has actually disappeared, someone has actually
그런데, 이 위키피디아 페이지는 실제로 사라졌기 때문에, 누군가가 실제로
replaced it with a Wikipedia page called On Green Threads.
라는 위키백과 페이지로 대체했습니다.
Anyway, there's a lot of interesting people kicking the tires.
어쨌든, 많은 흥미로운 사람들이 타이어를 차고 있습니다.
One of the things that surprised me a little bit is the number of people that actually
저를 조금 놀라게 한 것 중 하나는 실제로 다음과 같은 사람들이 있다는 것입니다.
were using virtual threads with things like re-implementing things like consensus algorithms
합의 알고리즘과 같은 것을 재구현하는 데 가상 스레드를 사용하고 있었다는 것입니다.
and doing a lot of things with blocking queues and other sort of CSP type things.
그리고 대기열을 차단하고 다른 종류의 CSP 유형으로 많은 작업을 수행했습니다.
That was actually interesting to go and see.
실제로 가서 보니 정말 흥미로웠어요.
So a lot of articles, literally hundreds of them, seemed to create quite a buzz.
말 그대로 수백 개에 달하는 많은 기사들이 꽤나 화제를 불러일으켰습니다.
And then there was many, many projects that actually spun up as well, which is actually
그리고 실제로 스핀업된 프로젝트도 정말 많았습니다.
interesting to see during this time frame.
이 기간 동안 흥미로웠습니다.
There was literally hundreds of people actually trying things out.
말 그대로 수백 명의 사람들이 실제로 무언가를 시도하고 있었습니다.
I think hats off to Elliot Barless because he dusted off things like Conway's Game of
엘리엇 바리스에게 경의를 표합니다. 그는 콘웨이의 게임 오브
Life using virtual threads.
가상 스레드를 사용하는 삶.
It was nice to see a puffer train going across the screen, which had 50,000 or 60,000 virtual
5만 또는 6만 개의 가상 스레드가 있는 화면을 가로지르는 복어 열차를 보는 것이 좋았습니다.
threads using blocking queues between them.
스레드 사이에 차단 대기열을 사용하는 것이 좋았습니다.
That was actually quite interesting.
사실 꽤 흥미로웠습니다.
I said about having a thread per task or thread per connection is one of his little demos
작업당 스레드 또는 연결당 스레드를 갖는 것에 대해 말씀드린 것은 그의 작은 데모 중 하나입니다.
actually had a little, I think it was a little chat server with 10 million TCP connections
실제로는 천만 개의 TCP 연결이 있는 작은 채팅 서버였던 것 같습니다.
with a virtual thread per connection.
연결당 가상 스레드를 사용했습니다.
That was actually cool to see.
정말 멋지네요.
And lots of other people did other interesting things as well.
다른 많은 사람들도 다른 재미있는 것들을 했어요.
Then queue all the frameworks, all the microservices frameworks.
그런 다음 모든 프레임워크와 모든 마이크로서비스 프레임워크를 대기열에 넣습니다.
We've all been looking at virtual threads as well.
가상 스레드도 살펴봤습니다.
From what I can see, I'm not familiar with all of these frameworks, of course, is they
물론 제가 보기에 이 모든 프레임워크에 익숙하지는 않습니다.
all seem to have come with some solution to be able to work with virtual threads.
모두 가상 스레드로 작업 할 수있는 솔루션이 제공된 것 같습니다.
Some of it is more deeply embedded than others.
일부는 다른 것보다 더 깊게 내장되어 있습니다.
Some are actually just doing handoff to virtual threads to run user code and so on.
일부는 실제로 사용자 코드 등을 실행하기 위해 가상 스레드에 핸드오프만 하고 있습니다.
But it's actually interesting to see.
하지만 실제로 보면 흥미롭습니다.
One of the things I like working on, what I like is that is JDK 21 only shipped very,
제가 작업하면서 좋아하는 것 중 하나는 JDK 21이 매우 빠르게 출시되었다는 것입니다,
very recently, but on that date, almost all of the frameworks actually had something working
아주 최근에 출시되었지만, 그 날짜에는 거의 모든 프레임워크가 실제로 작동하고 있었습니다.
with virtual threads.
가상 스레드로.
That was actually very, very nice to see.
정말 보기 좋네요.
One of the things on that slide was the Heladon folks is they went a little bit further actually
이 슬라이드의 내용 중 하나는 헬라돈 사람들이 실제로 조금 더 나아갔다는 것입니다.
than some of the other frameworks, or at least maybe they got off to an early start.
다른 프레임워크보다 더 빨리 시작했거나 적어도 일찍 시작했을 수도 있습니다.
Their existing core seemed to be based on Netty and Event Loop.
기존 핵심은 네티와 이벤트 루프를 기반으로 한 것 같습니다.
They started off with some very naive, simple importing to virtual threads, but they ran
매우 순진하고 간단한 가상 스레드 임포트로 시작했지만, 다음과 같이 실행되었습니다.
into a lot of problems because they were trying to use a lot of these libraries that depended
에 의존하는 많은 라이브러리를 사용하려고 했기 때문에 많은 문제가 발생했습니다.
on thread locals and native memory and things that didn't work too well with virtual threads.
스레드 로컬과 네이티브 메모리, 그리고 가상 스레드에서 잘 작동하지 않는 것들을 많이 사용하려고 했기 때문입니다.
I'll talk a bit more about that later on.
나중에 좀 더 자세히 설명하겠습니다.
What they decided to do, which was...
그들이 결정한 것은...
We lost the screen.
화면이 끊겼습니다.
Okay.
괜찮아
Can we see something's lost here?
여기서 뭔가 사라진 게 보여?
Anyway, what I'll say is that they re-implemented their core completely, replacing their Netty
어쨌든, 제가 말씀드리고 싶은 것은 그들이 네티를 대체하여 코어를 완전히 다시 구현했다는 것입니다.
core and replaced it with blocking IO.
코어를 차단 IO로 대체했습니다.
Believe it or not, they're actually using JavaNet Socket, which is a very, very simple
믿거나 말거나, 실제로는 매우 간단한 JavaNet 소켓을 사용하고 있습니다.
JDK one-year type of API.
JDK 1년형 API입니다.
Oh, we've something disconnected here.
여기 연결이 끊어졌습니다.
That was actually interesting to see.
정말 재미있네요.
Are we back?
돌아왔나?
Okay.
됐어.
I'll need to move on here because...
여기서 넘어가야겠어...
Okay, we have something back.
좋아, 뭔가 돌아왔어.
Okay, good.
좋아, 좋아.
What was interesting with their experiments is that by re-implementing their core with
이 실험에서 흥미로운 점은 코어를 다음과 같이 다시 구현함으로써
virtual threads and blocking IO, they were actually able to outperform their previous
가상 스레드로 코어를 재구현하고 IO를 차단함으로써 실제로 이전의
version of their microservices framework, which was very, very impressive to actually
마이크로서비스 프레임워크 버전을 능가할 수 있었는데, 이는 실제로 매우 인상적이었습니다.
go and see.
가서 보세요.
They've also published a whole bunch of performance data, and they seem to be quite comparable
그들은 또한 많은 성능 데이터를 발표했는데, 꽤 비슷한 것 같습니다.
with the other existing frameworks that are also in that space.
그 공간에 있는 다른 기존 프레임워크와도 꽤 비슷해 보입니다.
That was actually very, very interesting to see.
정말 흥미로웠어요.
We have a lot of usages already of virtual threads within the ecosystem.
이미 생태계 내에서 가상 스레드를 많이 사용하고 있습니다.
My colleague Ron Pressler and I, we've literally looked at dozens of articles and many, many
제 동료인 Ron Pressler와 저는 말 그대로 수십 개의 기사와 수많은
projects as to see how people are actually using virtual threads.
프로젝트를 통해 사람들이 실제로 가상 스레드를 어떻게 사용하는지 살펴봤습니다.
What we actually see is that some people, not all, are actually making mistakes.
실제로 모든 사람이 아니라 일부 사람들이 실제로 실수를 저지르고 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
Virtual threads, if you take one thing from this talk, is virtual threads are not magic
가상 스레드, 이 강연에서 한 가지를 취한다면 가상 스레드는 마법이 아니라는 것입니다.
pixie dust that you can actually just sprinkle over your existing code and actually make
실제로 기존 코드 위에 뿌려서 실제로 만들 수 있는 픽시 먼지가 아닙니다.
it faster.
더 빨리.
Making something run a virtual thread that doesn't make that code run any faster.
가상 스레드를 실행해도 코드가 더 빨리 실행되지 않습니다.
Where we see the mistakes making is people that are actually just blindly replacing platform
우리가 실수를 저지르는 곳은 실제로 맹목적으로 플랫폼을 교체하는 사람들입니다.
threads with virtual threads and expecting to see some difference.
스레드를 가상 스레드로 교체하고 어떤 차이를 기대하는 것입니다.
It doesn't always work like that.
항상 그렇게 작동하는 것은 아닙니다.
Also as well, we see people that are actually replacing the thread factory for thread pools
또한 스레드 풀을 위해 스레드 팩토리를 실제로 대체하는 사람들도 있습니다.
and actually replacing with a thread factory that creates virtual threads.
그리고 실제로 가상 스레드를 생성하는 스레드 팩토리로 대체하고 있습니다.
Well, virtual threads are not really intended to be pooled.
가상 스레드는 실제로 풀링을 위한 것이 아닙니다.
There's very, very few reasons why you would want to do this.
이렇게 해야 할 이유는 거의 없습니다.
Now, there is one issue we see, and I'll talk a little bit more about this later on in the
이제 한 가지 문제가 발견되었는데, 이 문제에 대해서는 나중에
talk, is we have this issue with pinning.
이야기에서 고정과 관련된 문제가 있습니다.
We have a quality of implementation issue where currently parking while holding a monitor
현재 모니터를 들고 주차하는 경우 구현 품질 문제가 있습니다.
doesn't release the underlying carrier thread.
기본 캐리어 스레드를 해제하지 않습니다.
That becomes a scalability issue, can lead to other issues like this.
이는 확장성 문제가 되고, 이와 같은 다른 문제로 이어질 수 있습니다.
A lot of developers that are kicking the tires of virtual threads are aware of this, but
가상 스레드를 사용하는 많은 개발자들이 이 사실을 알고 있습니다.
they're making the assumption that they've got to replace all usages of monitors with
로 모든 모니터 사용을 대체해야 한다는 가정을 하고 있습니다.
Java tilt concurrent locks.
자바 틸트 동시 잠금.
That isn't really the case.
실제로는 그렇지 않습니다.
It's understandable why there would be issues there.
왜 거기서 문제가 발생하는지 이해할 수 있습니다.
We also see an issue with there's a lot of libraries and frameworks that make use of
또한 다음과 같은 라이브러리와 프레임워크를 사용하는 많은 라이브러리와 프레임워크에도 문제가 있습니다.
thread locals.
스레드 로컬.
That's all okay, but there is a lot of libraries that just make the assumption that they're
괜찮지만, 다음과 같이 가정하는 라이브러리가 많이 있습니다.
always running a pooled thread.
항상 풀링된 스레드를 실행한다고 가정합니다.
They're caching some huge, big, mutable data in a thread local, and the assumption is that
스레드 로컬에 변경 가능한 대용량 데이터를 캐싱하고 있으며, 가정은 다음과 같습니다.
they're in a thread pool.
스레드 풀에 있다고 가정합니다.
That isn't the case when you actually are using virtual threads, because virtual threads
실제로 가상 스레드를 사용하는 경우에는 그렇지 않습니다.
are about having a new thread for each task.
는 각 작업에 대해 새 스레드를 갖는 것이기 때문입니다.
You're not going to get the benefit of those thread locals.
스레드 로컬의 이점을 얻지 못할 것입니다.
In fact, thread locals can actually work against you because you're creating one for every
사실, 스레드 로컬은 모든 스레드에 대해 하나씩 생성하기 때문에 실제로 불리하게 작용할 수 있다.
single task.
단일 작업마다.
We also see people publishing benchmarks that don't take into account a warmup.
또한 워밍업을 고려하지 않은 벤치마크를 게시하는 사람들도 있습니다.
We see people doing very, very complicated stuff, trying to mix blocking and non-blocking
블로킹과 비 블로킹을 혼합하여 매우 복잡한 작업을 수행하는 사람들을 볼 수 있습니다.
in I.O., and it ends up just being too complicated to reason about.
그리고 결국에는 추론하기에는 너무 복잡해지죠.
I suppose the summary from a lot of things that we've looked at is that sometimes there's
우리가 살펴본 많은 것들을 요약하면, 때때로 다음과 같은 경우가 있다는 것입니다.
a misunderstanding from where the performance benefits of Loom come from, or where the performance
Loom의 성능 이점이 어디에서 오는지, 또는 성능이 어디에서 오는지에 대한 오해입니다.
benefits of virtual threads come from.
가상 스레드의 이점이 어디에서 오는지에 대한 오해.
The benefit comes from their number, and it's as simple as that.
가상 스레드의 이점은 그 숫자에서 비롯되며, 간단합니다.
Here's a very important slide that we have.
여기에 매우 중요한 슬라이드가 있습니다.
Based on all these articles that we read and given our feeling for how we thought that
우리가 읽은 모든 기사를 바탕으로 우리가 어떻게 생각했는지에 대한 느낌을 주었습니다.
developers were understanding virtual threads, we have written up a number of points around
개발자들이 가상 스레드를 이해하고 있다고 생각하여 다음과 같은 몇 가지 요점을 정리했습니다.
migration or guidelines for how you actually move to virtual threads.
마이그레이션 또는 실제로 가상 스레드로 이동하는 방법에 대한 지침을 작성했습니다.
Number one point is keeping code as simple as possible.
가장 중요한 점은 코드를 최대한 단순하게 유지하는 것입니다.
Usynchronous blocking APIs is because virtual threads like blocking and simple code.
비동기 블로킹 API는 블로킹과 같은 가상 스레드와 간단한 코드를 사용하기 때문입니다.
Migrating to virtual threads is about migrating tasks to virtual threads, not platform threads
가상 스레드로 마이그레이션하는 것은 플랫폼 스레드가 아닌 가상 스레드로 작업을 마이그레이션하는 것입니다.
to virtual threads.
가상 스레드로 마이그레이션합니다.
That's an important point.
중요한 지점입니다.
One of the things with thread pools is that they work as a way of limiting concurrency.
스레드 풀의 장점 중 하나는 동시성을 제한하는 방식으로 작동한다는 것입니다.
If you have an infinite number or unbounded number of virtual threads, where do you want
가상 스레드 수가 무한대이거나 무제한인 경우, 어디에
to actually limit your concurrency?
로 동시성을 실제로 제한하고 싶으신가요?
Is it going to be your connections to your database?
데이터베이스에 대한 연결이 될까요?
Is it going to be something else?
다른 문제일까요?
There'll be some other bottleneck that's going to come out of the woodwork and some scalability
다른 병목 현상과 확장성 문제가 있을 겁니다.
bottleneck that you will have to reason about when using virtual threads.
가상 스레드를 사용할 때 추론해야 할 병목 현상이 있습니다.
Because of our quality of implementation issue at the moment with monitors, we have to avoid
현재 모니터의 구현 품질 문제로 인해, 우리는
scenarios where you're actually doing blocking I.O. and blocking for long periods of time
실제로 차단 I.O. 및 장시간 차단을 수행하는 시나리오를 피해야 합니다.
while holding monitors.
모니터를 들고 있는 동안
That's just an implementation limitation that we want to address.
이는 우리가 해결하고자 하는 구현상의 한계입니다.
These are the main points.
이것이 요점입니다.
We summarized them in JEP444.
JEP444에 요약했습니다.
JEP444 is the JEP that actually made virtual threads a permanent feature in Java 21.
JEP444는 실제로 Java 21에서 가상 스레드를 영구적인 기능으로 만든 JEP입니다.
We've also written an adoption guide at the end, which has a bit more detail on all of
또한 마지막에 채택 가이드를 작성했는데, 여기에는 다음과 같은 모든 사항에 대해 좀 더 자세히 설명되어 있습니다.
these points.
이 포인트에 대해 자세히 설명합니다.
I'll link that at the end as well.
이것도 마지막에 링크하겠습니다.
I want to move on and actually talk a little bit about structure concurrency.
이제 구조 동시성에 대해 조금 더 이야기하고 싶습니다.
This is something I've talked about briefly in previous presentations here, but we've
이전 프레젠테이션에서도 잠깐 언급했던 내용입니다.
moved on this feature for quite a bit since then.
그 이후로 이 기능에 대해 꽤 많은 작업을 진행했습니다.
The notion of structure concurrency isn't in any way a new concept.
구조체 동시성 개념은 결코 새로운 개념이 아닙니다.
It goes back decades.
수십 년 전으로 거슬러 올라갑니다.
But the term has come into use in the last couple of years.
하지만 이 용어는 지난 몇 년 동안 사용되기 시작했습니다.
Structure concurrency is really about treating groups of related tasks running in different
구조적 동시성은 실제로 서로 다른 곳에서 실행되는 관련 작업 그룹을 처리하는 것입니다.
threads as a single unit of work.
스레드를 하나의 작업 단위로 취급하는 것입니다.
It becomes important when we have virtual threads that make things very, very cheap
가상 스레드를 사용하면 매우 저렴하게 만들 수 있습니다.
to use.
사용할 수 있습니다.
We end up wondering how we would actually organize these groups of virtual threads.
이 가상 스레드 그룹을 실제로 어떻게 구성할지 궁금해집니다.
Another way to put it, and you'll see it in a lot of articles and blogs, is that structure
많은 기사와 블로그에서 볼 수 있는 또 다른 방법은 다음과 같은 구조입니다.
concurrency could be thought of as when control splits into multiple concurrent paths.
동시성은 제어가 여러 개의 동시 경로로 분할되는 경우로 생각할 수 있습니다.
We split, we decompose something into multiple concurrent subtasks, they must actually join
우리는 분할하고, 무언가를 여러 개의 동시 하위 작업으로 분해하고, 실제로 합류해야 합니다.
up again.
다시 올라갑니다.
That's really what the concept is all about.
이것이 바로 이 컨셉의 핵심입니다.
When you're dealing with concurrent programs, this is something that helps with the problems
동시 프로그램을 다룰 때 다음과 같은 문제를 해결하는 데 도움이 됩니다.
of cancellation and shutdown.
취소 및 종료합니다.
If you've read concurrency in practice, you'll know that this is a very problematic area
실제로 동시성을 읽어본 적이 있다면, 이것이 매우 문제가 많은 영역이라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
with concurrency, because it leads to things like problems with threads leaking or delaying
스레드 누수나 지연과 같은 문제가 발생하기 때문입니다.
with cancellation.
취소되었습니다.
I want to just show you a brief example, which is going to provide the motivation for the
간단한 예시를 보여드리고자 합니다.
types of things that we can actually do with the API that we've actually previewed in 21.
21에서 미리 살펴본 API로 실제로 할 수 있는 일의 유형을 보여드리겠습니다.
I'm going to show you a very, very simple, this is a boring piece of code.
아주 간단하고 지루한 코드를 보여드리겠습니다.
It's a method called handle that basically aggregates the results of two methods.
기본적으로 두 메서드의 결과를 합산하는 핸들이라는 메서드입니다.
One method fetches a username from somewhere, another fetches an order.
한 메서드는 어딘가에서 사용자 이름을 가져오고, 다른 메서드는 주문을 가져옵니다.
I have no idea what a user or an order is, just assume that they're doing something like
사용자나 주문이 무엇인지 모르겠지만, 그냥 다음과 같은 작업을 하고 있다고 가정합니다.
querying a database, accessing some remote endpoint.
데이터베이스 쿼리, 원격 엔드포인트 액세스.
They're doing something expensive.
뭔가 비싼 일을 하고 있습니다.
This is the sequential version of this piece of code.
이 코드의 순차 버전입니다.
If the find user method fails, throws an exception, in other words, the handle method will throw,
사용자 찾기 메서드가 실패하면 예외를 던집니다. 즉, 핸들 메서드가 예외를 던집니다,
we're all good.
모두 괜찮습니다.
If the find order method fails, throws an exception, the handle method throws, we're
찾기 순서 메서드가 실패하면 예외가 발생하고, 핸들 메서드가 예외를 발생하면 다음과 같습니다.
all good.
모두 정상입니다.
There's no cleanup actually required.
실제로 정리가 필요하지 않습니다.
Now, let's suppose we actually try to make these two methods actually run concurrently.
이제 실제로 이 두 메서드를 동시에 실행한다고 가정해 봅시다.
This is the concurrent version of it where I'm going to create, I'm going to use an executor
다음은 제가 만들 동시 실행 버전으로, 실행자를 사용하겠습니다.
service, which I've called executor in this example, and I'm going to submit two tasks
서비스(이 예제에서는 실행자라고 부릅니다)를 사용하여 두 개의 작업을 제출하겠습니다.
that will potentially run concurrently.
동시에 실행될 수 있습니다.
Then what we do is we're going to call the future get method.
그런 다음 미래의 get 메서드를 호출합니다.
By the way, if you're not familiar with executor service, it returns you back this thing called
참고로 실행자 서비스에 익숙하지 않다면, 이 메서드는
a promise or a future, it's called a future, and there's a get method which basically blocks
약속 또는 미래, 미래라고하며 기본적으로 차단하는 get 메서드가 있습니다.
waiting for the result.
결과를 기다립니다.
Aggregation is basically two gets.
집계는 기본적으로 두 개의 가져옴입니다.
Wait for the result to find user, wait for the result to find order, compose the response,
결과가 사용자를 찾을 때까지 기다리고, 결과가 순서를 찾을 때까지 기다렸다가 응답을 작성합니다,
we're done.
끝났습니다.
What's wrong with this code?
이 코드에 무슨 문제가 있나요?
Well, let's have a look what's wrong with this code.
이 코드에 무엇이 잘못되었는지 살펴봅시다.
If both of these tasks succeed, we're all good.
이 두 작업이 모두 성공하면 모두 정상입니다.
Get will return the user, order get will return the order, we create a response, we're all
Get은 사용자를 반환하고, order get은 주문을 반환하고, 응답을 생성하고, 모두 정상입니다.
good.
Now, let's actually think about what happens if one of these actually fail.
이제 이 중 하나가 실제로 실패하면 어떻게 되는지 생각해 봅시다.
Let's suppose the find user goes to some database and the database isn't available or something,
찾기 사용자가 어떤 데이터베이스로 이동했는데 해당 데이터베이스를 사용할 수 없다고 가정해 봅시다,
there's some error, and let's suppose that that task fails.
오류가 발생하여 해당 작업이 실패한다고 가정해 봅시다.
User.get is actually going to throw, which will cause handle to throw, but our task that's
User.get이 실제로 throw를 발생시켜 핸들을 던지겠지만, 우리의 태스크는
running find order is going to continue on running.
실행 중인 찾기 순서는 계속 실행됩니다.
We've got a bit of a leak there.
거기서 약간의 누수가 발생했습니다.
We haven't canceled the find order, it's just continuing to run.
찾기 명령을 취소하지 않고 계속 실행 중입니다.
Now, let's do the other way around where the find order was actually going to fail.
이제 실제로 찾기 명령이 실패할 경우를 반대로 해보겠습니다.
What's going to happen here is we're going to block for a long time waiting for find
여기서 일어날 일은 찾기를 기다리는 동안 오랫동안 차단하는 것입니다.
user and then we're going to call order get and it's going to throw and handle is going
사용자를 호출한 다음, get을 호출하고, 이 호출을 던져서
to throw.
던질 것입니다.
Okay, there's no additional cleanup to be done here, but I've wasted my time waiting
좋아, 여기서 추가로 정리할 건 없지만 기다리느라 시간을 낭비했어.
for find user to complete before I discover that find order fails.
사용자 찾기가 완료되기를 기다리느라 시간을 낭비했습니다.
Two things running concurrently, you kind of want to bail out when the first one fails.
두 가지 작업이 동시에 실행 중인데, 첫 번째 작업이 실패할 때 빠져나오고 싶을 것입니다.
These are the type of examples.
이러한 유형의 예제입니다.
We've actually got many, many examples like this where this motivated it to create a structure
실제로 이와 같은 예제에서 구조를 생성하도록 동기를 부여한 예제가 많이 있습니다.
concurrency API.
동시성 API.
I think when I presented here in 2018, we had prototype versions.
2018년에 여기서 발표했을 때는 프로토타입 버전이었던 것 같습니다.
We were using terminology like fiber and Fiberscope then sounded like a medical device, but it's
당시에는 파이버, 파이버스코프 같은 용어를 사용해 의료기기처럼 들리기도 했지만
since changed and it's now called Structured Task Scope in Java tool concurrent.
이후 변경되어 지금은 Java 도구 동시에서 구조화된 작업 범위라고 불립니다.
This is a preview API.
미리보기 API입니다.
We did have it in incubator module in 19 or 20 for people to actually to try out.
19년이나 20년에 사람들이 실제로 사용해 볼 수 있도록 인큐베이터 모듈에 포함시켰습니다.
This supports the general notion of actually structuring a task as a group of related sub
이는 실제로 작업을 관련 하위 작업 그룹으로 구성하는 일반적인 개념을 뒷받침합니다.
tasks and then trying to coordinate them as a unit.
작업의 그룹으로 구성한 다음 하나의 단위로 조정하려고 시도합니다.
It defines a fork method which goes and forks a thread to execute a sub task because virtual
가상 스레드가 하위 작업을 실행하기 위해 스레드를 포크하는 포크 메서드를 정의합니다.
threads are so cheap.
스레드가 너무 싸기 때문입니다.
The default is this is to go and fork a virtual thread.
기본값은 가상 스레드를 포크하는 것입니다.
We do fork, fork, fork, and then we do a join method.
포크, 포크, 포크를 반복한 다음 조인 메서드를 수행합니다.
This is a join that does a join as a unit.
이것은 하나의 단위로 조인을 수행하는 조인입니다.
By default, it's going to wait for all sub tasks to complete.
기본적으로 모든 하위 작업이 완료될 때까지 기다립니다.
That's kind of useful.
꽤 유용하네요.
It's one way.
한 가지 방법이야.
The overall shape of this API is that it's an auto-closable intended to be used with
이 API의 전체적인 모양은 다음과 함께 사용하도록 의도된 자동 폐쇄형입니다.
the tri-with resource construct.
와 함께 사용하기 위한 것입니다.
I'll show an example and then I want to talk through how it actually works.
예제를 보여드리고 실제로 어떻게 작동하는지 설명해드리겠습니다.
Here's our handle method rewritten to use Structured Task Scope.
다음은 구조화된 작업 범위를 사용하도록 재작성한 핸들 메서드입니다.
I'm using tri-with resources, so we create a Structured Task Scope.
트라이 위드 리소스를 사용하고 있으므로 구조화된 작업 범위를 생성합니다.
In this example, I'm using a Structured Task Scope called Shutdown on Failure.
이 예제에서는 실패 시 종료라는 구조화된 작업 범위를 사용하고 있습니다.
Shutdown on Failure is an implementation of Structured Task Scope that implements a policy
실패 시 종료는 정책을 구현하는 구조화된 작업 범위의 구현입니다.
to shut down the scope when any sub task fails.
하위 작업이 실패할 때 범위를 종료합니다.
It's a very, very simple policy.
아주 간단한 정책입니다.
We open it at the beginning by creating a Structured Task Scope and it gets closed at
구조화된 작업 범위를 생성하여 처음에 열면 다음에서 닫힙니다.
the end implicitly in this code because it's tri-with resources.
이 코드에서 암시적으로 끝은 리소스가 세 개이기 때문입니다.
What do we have inside the block here?
여기 블록 안에는 무엇이 있을까요?
We have fork, fork, join, and then we have some processing of the outcome.
포크, 포크, 조인, 그리고 결과에 대한 처리가 있습니다.
The two forks are exactly as this submit in the previous one.
두 개의 포크는 이전 제출한 것과 똑같습니다.
You give it the task or the sub task in this case and it goes and forks.
이 경우 태스크 또는 서브 태스크를 전달하면 두 개의 포크가 발생합니다.
It creates a new virtual thread, returns me back a handle in the form of a supplier in
새 가상 스레드를 생성하고, 공급자의 형태로 핸들을 반환합니다.
this example to the result.
의 핸들을 결과로 반환합니다.
We do our two forks.
두 개의 포크를 수행합니다.
Then we do a join.
그런 다음 조인을 수행합니다.
We're waiting for both of them.
둘 다 기다리고 있습니다.
In the case of Structured on Failure, it defines a method called throw a fail.
구조형 온 페일리의 경우 throw a fail라는 메서드를 정의합니다.
There's a whole variance of this one.
이것은 완전히 다릅니다.
What this does is it'll propagate the exception of the first one that fails.
이것이 하는 일은 실패한 첫 번째 예외를 전파하는 것입니다.
Those are the ways you can do mapping of exceptions and things like that.
이런 식으로 예외 매핑 등을 할 수 있습니다.
I'll just keep it simple for this example.
이 예제에서는 간단하게 해보겠습니다.
In the case that both succeeds, then we just aggregate the result from both.
둘 다 성공하면 둘의 결과를 합산합니다.
As a supplier, it defines a get method so you do get to get the result and we're all
공급자로서는 결과를 얻을 수 있도록 get 메서드를 정의하고 있습니다.
good.
좋아.
Somewhat similar shape to what we've seen in the previous examples, but we're only waiting
이전 예제에서 본 것과 다소 비슷한 모양이지만, 대기 중입니다.
once here, a single join.
여기서 한 번만 조인합니다.
What do we get from this?
이걸로 무엇을 얻을 수 있을까요?
Well, we're going to get error handling with short cutting.
단축 커팅으로 오류 처리를 할 수 있습니다.
We're going to get cleanup to avoid thread leaks.
스레드 누수를 방지하기 위해 정리를 하겠습니다.
We're going to avoid having delayed cancellation.
취소 지연을 피하려고 합니다.
Let's look at what happens when it succeeds.
성공하면 어떤 일이 일어나는지 살펴봅시다.
FindUser succeeds, findOrder succeeds, join wakes up when they're both completed, throw
FindUser가 성공하고, findOrder가 성공하고, 둘 다 완료되면 join이 깨어나고, throw
a fail does nothing because there's no exception, and we call the toGet methods, aggregate the
실패는 예외가 없으므로 아무 일도 하지 않으며, toGet 메서드를 호출하고
result and return it.
결과를 합산하여 반환합니다.
We're all good.
모두 정상입니다.
Now let's see what happens if findOrder fails.
이제 findOrder가 실패하면 어떻게 되는지 살펴봅시다.
FindUser running away, findOrder fails.
FindUser가 도망가고, findOrder는 실패합니다.
What happens is that leads to the shutdown of the scope, join method wakes up, and then
이로 인해 범위가 종료되고 조인 메서드가 깨어난 다음
we use the throw a fail that actually propagates the exception.
실제로 예외를 전파하는 throw a fail를 사용합니다.
Part of the shutdown on failure means that when findOrder fails, it cancels, by way of
실패 시 셧다운의 일부는 findOrder가 실패하면 다음과 같이 취소한다는 것을 의미합니다.
thread interruption, the other tasks that are running in this scope.
스레드 중단을 통해 이 범위에서 실행 중인 다른 작업을 취소합니다.
In this case, when findOrder fails, it will cancel findUser.
이 경우 findOrder가 실패하면 findUser가 취소됩니다.
The close method in this resources will ensure that it waits until any cleanup is done.
이 리소스의 close 메서드는 정리가 완료될 때까지 기다립니다.
If there's any stragglers or a little bit slow to respond to cancellation or interrupt,
지연자가 있거나 취소 또는 중단에 대한 응답이 약간 느린 경우,
then it waits for them to clean up so that you're not leaving any threads behind.
스레드가 남지 않도록 정리될 때까지 기다립니다.
Now let's look at the same thing when findUser fails.
이제 findUser가 실패할 때도 똑같이 살펴봅시다.
If findUser fails, then findOrder will be canceled by way of thread interrupt.
findUser가 실패하면 스레드 인터럽트를 통해 findOrder가 취소됩니다.
The join method will wake up, and throwOfIfFailed will propagate the exception.
조인 메서드가 깨어나고 throwOfIfFailed가 예외를 전파합니다.
So that's it.
이제 끝입니다.
It's a very simple API.
매우 간단한 API입니다.
So the example I've used is a shutdown on failure, which I said shuts down the task
그래서 제가 사용한 예제는 실패 시 작업을 종료하는 셧다운입니다.
scope when a subtask fails.
하위 작업이 실패할 때 종료합니다.
The API also has another built-in policy, which is called shutdown on success, which
API에는 성공 시 종료라는 또 다른 기본 제공 정책도 있습니다.
is like the equivalent of the invokeAny combinator, where when some subtask returns a result,
는 어떤 서브태스크가 결과를 반환할 때 invokeAny 결합자와 같은 역할을 합니다,
then you cancel the rest because you don't care about those.
를 반환하면 나머지는 신경 쓰지 않으므로 취소합니다.
The idea with this API, and this is one we need to get more feedback from usage, is that
이 API의 아이디어는, 그리고 우리가 사용으로부터 더 많은 피드백을 얻어야 하는 아이디어는 다음과 같습니다.
it can be extended to implement other policies.
다른 정책을 구현하도록 확장할 수 있다는 것입니다.
So it can be extended to do more collection of results.
따라서 더 많은 결과 수집을 수행하도록 확장할 수 있습니다.
It can be extended to go and define a...
확장하여 정의할 수 있습니다.
So that the subtask defines APIs that make available the outcome of the overall task
하위 태스크가 전체 태스크의 결과를 사용할 수 있는 API를 정의하도록 합니다.
to the main task.
메인 태스크에
And that's actually quite interesting, because both shutdown on failure and shutdown on success
실패 시 종료와 성공 시 종료가 모두 이루어지기 때문에 실제로 매우 흥미롭습니다.
also define specific APIs for dealing with results in those cases.
또한 이러한 경우 결과를 처리하기 위한 특정 API를 정의합니다.
Another thing just to say about structured task scope is it's not the end story on structured
구조화된 작업 범위에 대해 한 가지 더 말씀드리자면, 구조화된 작업 범위에 대한 이야기의 끝이 아닙니다.
concurrency.
동시성입니다.
This is all built on something that will allow us in the future to be able to define other
이 모든 것은 향후에 우리가 다른
structured concurrency APIs if we need it.
구조화된 동시성 API를 정의할 수 있습니다.
So right now, this API is in preview in Java 21.
현재 이 API는 Java 21에서 프리뷰 버전입니다.
I just spotted there's a typo on my slides as Java 11.
방금 슬라이드에 Java 11로 오타가 있는 것을 발견했습니다.
Ignore the typo.
오타는 무시하세요.
I should have canceled on fail there.
거기서 실패하면 취소했어야 했는데.
At this point, we expect to preview it again in 22.
이 시점에서 22시에 다시 미리 볼 수 있을 것으로 예상됩니다.
So that's all I'm going to say for the moment for structured concurrency.
구조적 동시성에 대한 설명은 여기까지입니다.
Now I want to move on and talk about thread locals.
이제 스레드 로컬에 대해 이야기하고 싶습니다.
So just a quick show of hands is who's used thread local?
그럼 누가 스레드 로컬을 사용해 보셨나요?
Okay, I think maybe about half of the people.
좋아, 아마 절반 정도일 거야.
Okay, so people know what this is all about.
좋아, 사람들은 이게 무슨 일인지 알겠군.
But if you haven't used it, it's really about just associating data with the current thread
하지만 사용해보지 않으셨다면 현재 스레드에 데이터를 연결하기만 하면 됩니다.
of execution.
실행하는 것입니다.
And thread local is a very, very general mechanism.
그리고 스레드 로컬은 매우 일반적인 메커니즘입니다.
It's been there since JDK 1.2.
JDK 1.2부터 있었습니다.
It's used for all sorts of things.
다양한 용도로 사용됩니다.
Frameworks and libraries love thread locals.
프레임워크와 라이브러리는 스레드 로컬을 좋아합니다.
They do all sorts of stuff with thread locals.
그들은 스레드 로컬로 모든 종류의 작업을 수행합니다.
And because it's such a general purpose mechanism, it's used for some wild and crazy things in
워낙 범용적인 메커니즘이기 때문에, 다음과 같은 엉뚱하고 미친 짓에 사용되기도 합니다.
some cases.
어떤 경우에는요.
But there are two things that it gets used for a lot.
하지만 두 가지 용도로 많이 사용됩니다.
One is caching.
하나는 캐싱입니다.
So if you've got threads in a thread pool, and when I say thread pool, I mean about a
따라서 스레드 풀에 스레드가 있고, 스레드 풀이라고 하면
thread that's running many, many tasks on the same thread of execution, it can provide
스레드가 동일한 실행 스레드에서 많은 작업을 실행하는 경우, 이 스레드는
a performance benefit for objects that are very, very expensive to create and are mutable.
생성 비용이 매우 많이 들고 변경 가능한 객체에 대한 성능 이점을 제공합니다.
They're not safe or they can be modified.
안전하지 않거나 수정할 수 있습니다.
It's a useful way for actually caching those things.
실제로 캐싱하는 데 유용한 방법입니다.
It's also used by frameworks for supporting things like callbacks, be able to get data
또한 콜백 같은 것을 지원하기 위해 프레임워크에서 사용되며, 데이터를 가져올 수 있습니다.
from my call to the API to somewhere, some faraway callee, which is the callback.
API에 대한 내 호출에서 멀리 떨어진 호출자, 즉 콜백으로 데이터를 전송합니다.
So it's essentially working as an implicit parameter in that case.
따라서 이 경우에는 기본적으로 암시적 매개변수로 작동합니다.
There's other libraries use it for things like implicit return values as well.
다른 라이브러리에서도 암시적 반환값과 같은 용도로 사용합니다.
I'm not going to get into that.
그 얘기는 하지 않겠습니다.
There's a lot of issues with thread locals.
스레드 로컬에 많은 문제가 있습니다.
Those that put up their hands to use thread locals, I'm guessing is that some percentage
스레드 로컬을 사용하겠다고 손을 든 사람들은, 아마도 몇 퍼센트가
of you have had problems with so-called memory leaks and thread locals.
중 일부는 소위 메모리 누수 및 스레드 로컬에 문제가 있었을 것입니다.
So some piece of code goes and stashes its collection of cats in a thread local, and
그래서 어떤 코드가 스레드 로컬에 고양이 컬렉션을 숨겨놓고
it's a gigabyte of cats, and that thread just continues forever.
기가바이트의 고양이가 저장되고 그 스레드는 영원히 계속됩니다.
That's a lot of memory wasted, even though the other subtasks that run on that never
그 스레드에서 실행되는 다른 서브 태스크는 절대 실행되지 않음에도 불구하고 많은 메모리가 낭비됩니다.
make use of that code again.
그 코드를 다시 사용해야 합니다.
Other issues with it is that there's essentially this problem of unconstrained immutability.
다른 문제점은 본질적으로 제약되지 않은 불변성이라는 문제가 있다는 것입니다.
If you have access to the thread local, you can actually change its value.
로컬에서 스레드에 접근할 수 있다면 실제로 값을 변경할 수 있습니다.
Inheritance is problematic with thread local.
스레드 로컬에서 상속이 문제가 있습니다.
When we do corpus scans of code bases, we don't see a huge amount of inheritable thread
코드 베이스의 말뭉치 스캔을 수행하면 상속 가능한 스레드의 양이 엄청나게 많지 않습니다.
local usage because it's so expensive.
너무 비싸기 때문에 로컬 사용.
It's inheritance at creation time.
생성 시 상속입니다.
So there's a lot of issues there.
그래서 많은 문제가 있습니다.
Main things that I think that people run into with thread locals is just the issue around lifetime.
제가 생각하는 스레드 로컬에서 사람들이 겪는 주요 문제는 수명에 관한 문제입니다.
They don't get cleaned up unless they're explicitly cleaned up.
명시적으로 정리하지 않는 한 정리되지 않습니다.
Okay, so virtual threads and thread locals.
좋아, 가상 스레드와 스레드 로컬.
This is where it gets kind of interesting, is that virtual threads are threads.
여기서 흥미로운 점이 있는데, 가상 스레드는 스레드라는 점입니다.
Therefore they must support thread locals.
따라서 스레드 로컬을 지원해야 합니다.
It's kind of a forced move because there's so much existing code uses thread locals.
스레드 로컬을 사용하는 기존 코드가 너무 많기 때문에 어쩔 수 없이 변경한 것입니다.
We did at one point attempt to provide a way to opt out of supporting thread locals when
한때 스레드 로컬 지원을 거부할 수 있는 방법을 제공하려고 시도한 적이 있습니다.
creating virtual threads, but it was problematic for running existing code.
가상 스레드를 생성할 때 스레드 로컬 지원을 거부하는 방법을 제공하려고 했지만, 기존 코드를 실행하는 데 문제가 있었습니다.
It meant some kind of bifurcation of the ecosystem in that this is code that runs on a platform
이것은 플랫폼에서 실행되는 코드라는 점에서 생태계의 일종의 분기점을 의미했습니다.
thread, it can use thread locals.
스레드를 사용하면 스레드 로컬을 사용할 수 있습니다.
This is code that can't use thread locals.
스레드 로컬을 사용할 수 없는 코드입니다.
That's not a good place to be, so we backed away from that.
좋은 위치가 아니므로 여기서 물러났습니다.
Why it's problematic for virtual threads is because remember we're migrating from tasks
가상 스레드에 문제가 있는 이유는 우리가 작업에서 마이그레이션하고 있다는 것을 기억하기 때문입니다.
to virtual threads, not platform threads to virtual threads.
에서 가상 스레드로 마이그레이션하는 것이지 플랫폼 스레드에서 가상 스레드로 마이그레이션하는 것이 아닙니다.
So if a virtual thread and a task is a one-to-one relationship, then if the first use of some
따라서 가상 스레드와 태스크가 일대일 관계인 경우, 처음 사용하는 경우
library creates some expensive object, stashes it in the thread local and never uses it again,
라이브러리는 값비싼 객체를 생성하여 스레드 로컬에 저장하고 다시는 사용하지 않습니다,
that's going to penalize all usages of that code running in virtual threads.
가상 스레드에서 실행되는 해당 코드의 모든 사용에 불이익을 줄 것입니다.
And caching can be very, very negative, particularly with some of the modern garbage collectors.
그리고 캐싱은 특히 최신 가비지 컬렉터 중 일부에서 매우 부정적인 영향을 미칠 수 있습니다.
So when we want to migrate to using virtual threads, we have to start thinking about our
따라서 가상 스레드 사용으로 마이그레이션하고 싶을 때, 우리는 우리의
thread local usage.
스레드 로컬 사용량을 고려해야 합니다.
There's some diagnostics and stuff for helping to detect some of these things.
이러한 것들을 감지하는 데 도움이 되는 몇 가지 진단 및 기능이 있습니다.
The main thing is thinking about, do I really need to cache this expensive object in a thread
가장 중요한 것은 이 비싼 객체를 스레드에 캐시할 필요가 있느냐는 것입니다.
local?
If it's a mutable object, is there some immutable alternative that I should use?
변경 가능한 객체라면 제가 사용해야 할 불변 대체물이 있나요?
A good example is when we do corpus analysis, we find many, many classes are actually stashing
좋은 예는 말뭉치 분석을 할 때 많은 클래스가 실제로 숨어있는 것을 발견하는 것입니다.
away a simple date format in a static final thread local.
정적 최종 스레드 로컬에 간단한 날짜 형식을 숨기고 있습니다.
Why are they doing that?
왜 저러는 걸까요?
Because these simple date formatters are expensive to create and they're mutable.
이러한 간단한 날짜 포맷터는 만드는 데 비용이 많이 들고 변경이 가능하기 때문입니다.
But there's a better alternative with the Java time API and Java time formatter that
하지만 Java 시간 API와 Java 시간 포맷터를 사용하면 더 나은 대안이 있습니다.
allows me to store that as an immutable object in a static final field, and I don't need
를 사용하면 정적 최종 필드에 불변 객체로 저장할 수 있으며, 이를 위해
a thread local.
를 로컬 스레드에 저장할 필요가 없습니다.
And there's other examples of this kind of thing.
이런 종류의 다른 예도 있습니다.
There's other cases where using some cache or some other kind of more interesting caching
캐시나 다른 종류의 더 흥미로운 캐싱을 사용하는 다른 사례도 있습니다.
can avoid using these thread locals as well.
를 사용하면 이러한 스레드 로컬 사용을 피할 수 있습니다.
So I guess our message when we're migrating to virtual threads is moving away from thread
따라서 가상 스레드로 마이그레이션할 때 우리의 메시지는 스레드에서 멀어지고 있다는 것입니다.
locals if it makes sense.
로 이동하는 것 같습니다.
In the JDK and particularly in the base module, base module is the core module of the Java
JDK, 특히 베이스 모듈에서 베이스 모듈은 Java의 핵심 모듈입니다.
platform.
플랫폼의 핵심 모듈입니다.
One of the exercises we did over the last couple of releases is we evaluated the usages
지난 몇 번의 릴리스에서 수행한 연습 중 하나는 사용량을 평가하는 것입니다.
of thread locals in many, many areas and found that they had negative performance.
의 스레드 로컬 사용량을 평가한 결과 성능이 저하되는 것을 확인했습니다.
They were added as caching, some performance solution many, many years ago.
수년 전에 캐싱, 일부 성능 솔루션으로 추가되었습니다.
But since then, we've moved to G1, there's basically better garbage collection and better
하지만 그 이후로 우리는 G1으로 이전했고, 기본적으로 가비지 컬렉션이 더 좋아졌고, 더 나은
VM implementation means that the caching ends up having negative benefits rather than
VM 구현은 캐싱이 결국 부정적인 이점을 가지게 된다는 것을 의미합니다.
positive benefits.
긍정적 이점이 있습니다.
So we were able to reimplement and re-implement that part of code and get rid of the caching.
따라서 해당 코드 부분을 다시 구현하고 재구현하여 캐싱을 제거할 수 있었습니다.
And I think as well as this is, I should say, is this is a part of Project Loom is we've
그리고 이것뿐만 아니라 프로젝트 룸의 한 부분이라고 해야 할까요?
had to explore a number of other possible APIs as alternatives for thread locals for
에 대한 스레드 로컬의 대안으로 가능한 다른 여러 API를 탐색해야 했습니다.
particular use cases.
특정 사용 사례.
I'm not going to talk about these in any detail today, but maybe previous presentations you
오늘은 이에 대해 자세히 설명하지는 않겠지만, 이전 프레젠테이션에서 다음과 같이 설명한 적이 있을 것입니다.
would have seen us talk about things like processor locals and a few other things like
에서 프로세서 로컬과 같은 것들에 대해 이야기하는 것을 보셨을 것입니다.
that.
그.
The one I do want to talk about is the common use case of the callbacks are essentially
제가 이야기하고 싶은 것은 콜백의 일반적인 사용 사례입니다.
using thread locals as a form of implicit parameter.
스레드 로컬을 암시적 매개변수의 한 형태로 사용하는 것입니다.
It's essentially transmission of some data to some faraway colleague, typically a callback
본질적으로 멀리 떨어진 동료에게 일부 데이터를 전송하는 것인데, 일반적으로 콜백입니다.
without using a method parameter.
메서드 매개변수를 사용하지 않고.
So I want to talk about that type of usage because we've added this API.
이 API를 추가했기 때문에 이러한 유형의 사용법에 대해 이야기하고 싶습니다.
It's actually Andrew Haley actually added this effort.
실제로 이 작업을 추가한 것은 앤드류 헤일리입니다.
We've added this as a scope value API, as a preview API in 21, which specifically targets
21에서 미리보기 API로 범위 값 API로 추가했으며, 특히 다음 대상을 대상으로 합니다.
this use case in a very nice way and essentially provides both a safe and a very efficient
이 사용 사례는 매우 멋진 방식으로, 본질적으로 안전하고 매우 효율적인
way of actually sharing to callbacks without using method parameters.
메서드 매개변수를 사용하지 않고 콜백에 실제로 공유할 수 있는 방법을 제공합니다.
All of the frames in between the framework and the callback have no access to this implicit
프레임워크와 콜백 사이에 있는 모든 프레임은 이 암시적 프레임에 접근할 수 없습니다.
or hidden parameter, if you like.
또는 원하는 경우 숨겨진 매개변수에 액세스할 수 있습니다.
So here's a motivating example.
여기 동기부여가 되는 예시가 있습니다.
I've just taken a stack trace because I like showing slides with stack traces.
스택 트레이스로 슬라이드를 표시하는 것이 좋아서 방금 스택 트레이스를 찍었습니다.
This one here is just...
이건 그냥...
I don't know what half the components are in here.
여기 구성 요소의 절반이 뭔지 모르겠어요.
There's Jetty, Jersey, HK2, and a whole bunch of other stuff in this stack trace.
이 스택 추적에는 제티, 저지, HK2 및 기타 여러 가지가 있습니다.
Oh, by the way, when looking at stack traces in my slides, they all start at the bottom
아참, 슬라이드에서 스택 트레이스를 보면 모두 아래쪽부터 시작하네요.
up, but other people like to do a top down.
위쪽에서 시작하지만 다른 사람들은 위에서 아래로 하는 것을 좋아합니다.
But for this slide, bottom up is where the initial frame is.
하지만 이 슬라이드의 경우 초기 프레임이 있는 곳이 상향식입니다.
Now I want to zoom in on just a little small portion of this stack trace, and hopefully
이제 이 스택 트레이스의 아주 작은 부분만 확대하고 싶습니다.
it's actually readable here.
여기서 읽을 수 있기를 바랍니다.
Because when we actually zoom in here, I actually see a callback.
실제로 여기를 확대하면 콜백이 보이니까요.
In fact, you can actually zoom in on a couple of parts of this, and there's actually many,
실제로 이 부분의 몇 가지를 확대하면 실제로 많은 부분이 있습니다,
many callbacks.
많은 콜백이 있습니다.
But I've just picked one of them.
하지만 방금 그중 하나를 골랐어요.
And this callback is something in some code called Jersey, which I think is something
그리고 이 콜백은 저지(Jersey)라는 코드에 있는 것인데, 제가 생각하기에는
in the Jax-RS area, where it's got this method called run in scope, where I see it actually
라는 메서드가 있는데, 이 메서드에는 범위 내에서 실행이라는 메서드가 있습니다.
sets a thread local, and then further in the call chain, we see it calling request
는 스레드를 로컬로 설정한 다음 호출 체인에서 더 나아가 요청을 호출하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
scope dot current.
스코프 도트 전류.
So what's going on here is the framework called Jersey is setting some thread local, and then
여기서 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지는 Jersey라는 프레임워크가 일부 스레드를 로컬로 설정한 다음
it's reading it way further on in the execution with this request scope dot current.
이 요청 범위 도트 전류로 실행에서 훨씬 더 멀리 읽습니다.
So it's doing a set in one place, get another.
그래서 한 곳에서 세트를 수행하고 다른 세트를 가져옵니다.
It's basically providing some context or data, or let's call it some context scope
기본적으로 컨텍스트 또는 데이터를 제공하거나 컨텍스트 범위라고 부를 수 있습니다.
thing.
같은 거요.
And it's making it available to the callback without using a parameter.
그리고 매개변수를 사용하지 않고 콜백에서 사용할 수 있도록 합니다.
That's actually interesting to see.
정말 흥미롭습니다.
And as I say, many of the frameworks, you actually see this.
그리고 제가 말씀드린 것처럼 많은 프레임워크에서 실제로 이것을 볼 수 있습니다.
Now let's look at what this code might look like.
이제 이 코드가 어떻게 생겼는지 살펴봅시다.
This, by the way, is not the code from Jersey.
그건 그렇고, 이것은 저지의 코드가 아닙니다.
This is just sort of a simplified version, just to give you an idea of what's actually
이것은 일종의 단순화 된 버전으로, 실제로 무엇이 있는지 아이디어를 제공하기 위해
going on.
진행 중입니다.
So I've got this run in scope method that's setting a thread local, and then there's a
그래서 스레드를 로컬로 설정하는 범위 내에서 실행하는 메서드가 있고, 그 다음
current method that actually returns the thread local.
현재 메서드가 실제로 스레드를 로컬로 반환합니다.
And the thread local, the value in this case, is of type of request context, which I've
그리고 이 경우의 값인 스레드 로컬은 요청 컨텍스트 유형입니다.
just made up, by the way.
방금 만들어낸 값입니다.
It's not what this code uses.
이 코드가 사용하는 것이 아닙니다.
Now if we focus on just a little piece of this code, let's actually go and see what's
이제 이 코드의 일부분만 집중해서 살펴봅시다.
actually going on.
실제로 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지 살펴봅시다.
So it creates one of these request context objects.
따라서 이러한 요청 컨텍스트 객체 중 하나가 생성됩니다.
Remember, we don't know what that is.
기억하세요, 우리는 그것이 무엇인지 모릅니다.
And it's setting it as a thread local, making a call to something called errors dot process.
그리고 스레드 로컬로 설정하고 오류 도트 프로세스라는 것을 호출하고 있습니다.
I have no idea what that does.
그게 뭘 하는 건지 모르겠어요.
And then it's got a finally block where it's actually going to remove the thread local.
그리고 마지막으로 실제로 스레드를 로컬로 제거하는 블록이 있습니다.
Now this code and this framework thing seems to be able to support kind of nested type
이제 이 코드와 이 프레임워크는 일종의 중첩된 유형을 지원할 수 있는 것 같습니다.
of context.
의 컨텍스트를 지원합니다.
So this is essentially working like a stack.
따라서 이것은 본질적으로 스택처럼 작동합니다.
It fetches the, gets the current value of the thread local, saves that, sets it to some
로컬 스레드의 현재 값을 가져와서 저장한 다음, 이를 일부
new value, calls whatever the code is, and then the finally block is actually essentially
새 값으로 설정하고, 코드가 무엇이든 호출한 다음, 최종적으로 블록은 실제로 본질적으로
a restore.
복원이 됩니다.
So the restore is either restoring it to the previous value, or it's doing a remove.
따라서 복원은 이전 값으로 복원하거나 제거를 수행합니다.
This is a kind of a pattern that we see in quite a few frameworks.
이것은 꽤 많은 프레임워크에서 볼 수 있는 일종의 패턴입니다.
And it's just one example of using implicit parameters.
이는 암시적 매개변수 사용의 한 예시일 뿐입니다.
So let's go and look at this equivalent code using a scoped value.
이제 범위 지정 값을 사용하는 이와 동등한 코드를 살펴보겠습니다.
Now this is a little bit shorter, just because scope value kind of supports this thing.
범위 값이 이것을 지원하기 때문에 이것은 조금 더 짧습니다.
So the scope value is the first of the top.
그래서 범위 값은 맨 위의 첫 번째입니다.
We actually see there's a request context.
실제로 요청 컨텍스트가 있음을 알 수 있습니다.
It's a static final field as well.
정적 최종 필드이기도 합니다.
And it has a type parameter for the request context.
그리고 요청 컨텍스트에 대한 타입 매개변수도 있습니다.
So it's kind of similar to thread local in terms of its setup and the access control
따라서 설정과 접근 제어 측면에서 스레드 로컬과 비슷합니다.
that you typically use to guard access to the scope value field itself.
일반적으로 범위 값 필드 자체에 대한 액세스를 보호하는 데 사용합니다.
We create a request context as before.
이전과 마찬가지로 요청 컨텍스트를 생성합니다.
And then what we're going to do is we're actually going to run a piece of code with the scope
그런 다음 실제로 다음 범위의 코드를 실행합니다.
value set some new request context that I create.
값으로 제가 만든 새로운 요청 컨텍스트를 설정합니다.
So what we see here is scope value dot run where, and then you've got essentially a key
따라서 여기서 볼 수 있는 것은 범위 값 도트 실행 위치이며, 본질적으로 키
and a value.
와 값
So the key is the request context variable, and then the request context value.
따라서 키는 요청 컨텍스트 변수이고, 그다음은 요청 컨텍스트 값입니다.
And then in this case, it's a runnable.
그리고 이 경우에는 런처블입니다.
There's variations of this for callables and suppliers.
콜러블과 공급자에 대한 변형이 있습니다.
But the point is this sets up a binding for the duration of the errors dot process method.
하지만 요점은 이것이 오류 도트 프로세스 메서드의 지속 시간에 대한 바인딩을 설정한다는 것입니다.
So when that method actually completes, the binding is removed or restored to its previous
따라서 해당 메서드가 실제로 완료되면 바인딩이 제거되거나 이전으로 복원됩니다.
value.
값으로 복원됩니다.
And that's actually very, very nice because we don't have any leakage here.
여기에는 누수가 전혀 없으니 정말 아주 좋은 결과입니다.
We're not leaving anything behind.
우리는 아무것도 남기지 않을 거야.
This is actually really, really nice to use.
이건 정말 사용하기 정말 좋네요.
So just a quick summary on scope value is this.
범위 값에 대한 간단한 요약은 다음과 같습니다.
When this API becomes permanent, this would be the preferred way of doing essentially
이 API가 영구화되면, 기본적으로 다음과 같은 방식이 선호될 것입니다.
the one-way transmission.
단방향 전송입니다.
It's how you will actually do implicit parameters.
이것이 실제로 암시적 매개변수를 수행하는 방법입니다.
It's how to support the callbacks type of use case.
콜백 유형의 사용 사례를 지원하는 방법입니다.
It's a lot better than thread locals for this type of use case.
이러한 유형의 사용 사례에는 스레드 로컬보다 훨씬 낫습니다.
One reason is that your faraway callee can't change the binding.
한 가지 이유는 멀리 있는 캘리가 바인딩을 변경할 수 없기 때문입니다.
It can establish a new binding and call additional code, but it can't change the existing binding.
새 바인딩을 설정하고 추가 코드를 호출할 수는 있지만 기존 바인딩을 변경할 수는 없습니다.
This bounded lifetime, because as I said, it's a where method.
이 바인딩 수명은 앞서 말했듯이 where 메서드이기 때문입니다.
It's bound for the duration of the, in this case, the runnable.
이 경우에는 실행 가능한 기간 동안 바인딩됩니다.
It actually works with inheritance and in structured context.
실제로 상속과 구조화된 컨텍스트에서 작동합니다.
So this is actually kind of interesting.
그래서 이것은 사실 좀 흥미롭습니다.
I'm not going to show it to you because we don't have too much time.
시간이 많지 않아서 보여드리지 않겠습니다.
But if we combine it with our structure concurrency where we actually decompose some task into
하지만 실제로 어떤 작업을 다음과 같이 분해하는 구조 동시성과 결합하면
multiple subtasks, you can actually inherit the scope value into all of the subtasks transparently.
여러 개의 서브 태스크로 분해하면 실제로 모든 서브 태스크에 범위 값을 투명하게 상속할 수 있습니다.
And that's actually really, really nice.
정말 정말 좋은 기능입니다.
And performance-wise, this is actually better than a thread local.
성능 측면에서는 실제로 스레드 로컬보다 낫습니다.
It's optimized.
최적화되었습니다.
The access to a scope value is close to the accessing a field, which is really, really
범위 값에 대한 액세스는 필드에 액세스하는 것과 비슷합니다.
nice.
Now, in terms of status of this API, we're going to need more feedback and real-world
이제 이 API의 상태와 관련하여 더 많은 피드백과 실제 세계가 필요합니다.
usage before it becomes a permanent API.
사용량이 더 필요합니다.
So it's likely preview again in 22.
따라서 22시에 다시 미리보기가 될 가능성이 높습니다.
OK.
So overall current status then of where we are with virtual threads.
가상 스레드에 대한 전반적인 현재 상태입니다.
So as I said, it became a permanent feature in Java 21.
앞서 말했듯이 자바 21의 영구적인 기능이 되었습니다.
I think overall, it's been very well received by the ecosystem.
전반적으로 생태계에서 매우 호평을 받고 있다고 생각합니다.
I think there's a lot of interest in going back to simple, maintainable blocking code
단순하고 유지 관리가 가능한 차단 코드로 돌아가는 것에 많은 관심이 있는 것 같습니다.
just to avoid the more complicated and hard to maintain async type of code.
더 복잡하고 유지 관리가 어려운 비동기식 코드를 피하기 위해서 말이죠.
Most of the mainstream frameworks have got something working with virtual threads.
대부분의 주류 프레임워크는 가상 스레드와 함께 작동하는 무언가를 가지고 있습니다.
Some of it mightn't be all that efficient for a first version.
첫 번째 버전에서는 그다지 효율적이지 않을 수도 있습니다.
There might be a lot of additional handoff going on.
추가적으로 많은 핸드오프가 진행될 수 있습니다.
But it's nice to have something working on day one.
그래도 첫날부터 뭔가 작동하는 게 있으니 좋네요.
Overall, the performance has actually been really, really, really good in terms of the
전반적으로 성능은 실제로 정말, 정말, 정말 좋았습니다.
runtime support.
런타임 지원.
There's a couple of exceptions that are a little bit problematic, particularly with
특히 다음과 같이 약간 문제가 되는 몇 가지 예외가 있습니다.
profilers and JVMTI.
프로파일러와 JVMTI.
That's something that's being worked on.
작업 중입니다.
Reliability has actually been quite good.
안정성은 실제로 꽤 좋았어요.
There's been very few issues around that.
관련 문제도 거의 없었습니다.
The main thing that's coming up is pinning, which this is, of course, not something we
가장 중요한 것은 고정인데, 물론 이것은 저희가
raced into.
달려들었죠.
The limitation is that for 21, the synchronization is problematic.
21의 경우 동기화에 문제가 있다는 한계가 있습니다.
As I said, the other APIs, the Structured Concurrency and Scope Value API, they are
앞서 말했듯이 다른 API인 구조화된 동시성 및 범위 값 API는 다음과 같습니다.
preview for 21.
21에 대한 미리보기.
That's the current status of things.
현재 상태입니다.
Looking forward then, where are we?
그럼 어디까지 왔죠?
We'll likely do a second preview of the two APIs mentioned.
앞서 언급한 두 가지 API에 대한 두 번째 프리뷰를 진행할 예정입니다.
We need to get more feedback before we can make them permanent.
영구화하기 전에 더 많은 피드백이 필요합니다.
There is ongoing work for Java monitors.
자바 모니터에 대한 작업이 진행 중입니다.
We know that this is actually a pain point.
이것이 실제로 고충이라는 것을 알고 있습니다.
There's actually two efforts going on.
실제로 두 가지 작업이 진행 중입니다.
One is the longer term reimplementation of Java monitors.
하나는 자바 모니터의 장기적인 재구현입니다.
I can't say which release this will actually show up in.
이것이 실제로 어느 릴리스에 나타날지는 말할 수 없습니다.
This is many person years of work touching many, many areas.
많은 사람이 수년간 많은 분야에 걸쳐 작업한 결과물입니다.
However, we have a shorter term direction that's currently being worked on, which is
하지만 현재 작업 중인 단기적인 방향은 다음과 같습니다.
change the existing Java monitors implementation to be more friendly to virtual threads.
기존 Java 모니터 구현을 가상 스레드에 더 친화적으로 변경하는 것입니다.
This will allow when you're parking while holding a monitor, it allows the carrier to
이렇게 하면 모니터를 들고 주차할 때 캐리어가
be released.
이 해제됩니다.
It'll also allow us to deal with the contended case.
또한 경합 중인 사건을 처리할 수 있습니다.
Contended monitor entry will allow us to release the carrier.
경합 모니터 진입으로 캐리어를 해제할 수 있습니다.
Then, further along, we want to also try to release the carrier for object at wait.
그리고 더 나아가 대기 중인 객체에 대해서도 캐리어를 해제하려고 합니다.
The nice thing about this is all these pieces don't actually have to come together.
이 작업의 좋은 점은 이 모든 조각들이 실제로 함께 모일 필요가 없다는 것입니다.
They can actually be split up a little bit.
실제로는 약간 분할할 수 있습니다.
This is good.
이거 좋네요.
This is all very promising.
매우 유망하군요.
Maybe at some point, we'll actually have some Loom early access builds with this for people
언젠가는 실제로 이 기능이 포함된 Loom 얼리 액세스 빌드를 사람들에게 제공할 수 있을지도 모르겠네요.
actually to try out.
실제로 사용해볼 수 있게요.
This is the short term thing.
이것은 단기적인 것입니다.
The longer term is reimplementation of monitors.
장기적으로는 모니터 재구현입니다.
There's a whole bunch of things going on at the moment around performance and footprint,
현재 성능과 설치 공간과 관련하여 많은 일이 일어나고 있습니다,
particularly around compression of stack frames.
특히 스택 프레임 압축과 관련해서는요.
We've got some scalability issues with timers that we want to work on.
타이머와 관련된 몇 가지 확장성 문제를 해결해야 합니다.
File IO and some of the operating system integration is something that needs improvement.
파일 IO와 일부 운영 체제 통합은 개선이 필요한 부분입니다.
Also, JVM TI performance is problematic.
또한 JVM TI 성능에 문제가 있습니다.
There's also work going on around serviceability.
서비스 가능성 관련 작업도 진행 중입니다.
A lot of the serviceability budget was spent twice over getting the debugger working with
서비스 가능성 예산의 상당 부분이 디버거를 작동시키는 데 두 번이나 사용되었습니다.
virtual threads at the cost of or the expense of some of the other serviceability features.
가상 스레드에 대한 비용 또는 다른 서비스 가능성 기능의 일부를 희생했습니다.
At the moment, thread dumps that include virtual threads don't include lock information, deadlock
현재 가상 스레드를 포함하는 스레드 덤프에는 잠금 정보, 교착 상태, 데드락이 포함되지 않습니다.
detection.
감지.
That's not something we need to work on.
그건 우리가 해결해야 할 문제가 아닙니다.
We need to expose in the more medium long term is better APIs for some of the tooling
중장기적으로는 일부 툴링에 대해 더 나은 API를 노출해야 합니다.
to be able to enumerate threads.
스레드를 열거할 수 있도록 수정했습니다.
That's currently what will happen beyond JDK 21.
이것이 현재 JDK 21 이후에 일어날 일입니다.
Just then, a couple of links.
바로 그 때, 몇 개의 링크가 있습니다.
The link to the JEP and the adoption guide.
JEP 및 채택 가이드 링크입니다.
Remember the migration to virtual threads is important.
가상 스레드로의 마이그레이션이 중요하다는 것을 기억하세요.
Link to the other JEPs and the mailing list.
다른 JEP와 메일링 리스트에 링크합니다.
That's all I have for now.
지금은 여기까지입니다.
We have two minutes for questions.
질문할 시간이 2분 남았습니다.
If anyone wants to shout, then please do.
외치고 싶은 사람 있으면 외쳐주세요.
Mario.
마리오.
Can you go back to the structure and concurrency example?
구조와 동시성 예제로 돌아가 볼까요?
Yeah.
네
Sorry.
죄송합니다.
Sorry, where is me?
미안, 나 어디 있어?
OK.
Let's look at this guy.
이 녀석 좀 보자.
Just to understand if I'm understanding correctly.
내가 제대로 이해했는지 확인하려고.
This one does the same thing of combining two completable features, right?
이것도 완성 가능한 두 기능을 결합하는 것과 같은 일을 하는 거죠?
The question is, is this combining,
문제는 이게 결합이냐는 거죠,
is this a bit like computable futures?
계산 가능한 선물과 비슷한가요?
And the answer is yes, but more in a synchronous
대답은 '예'이지만 동기식 선물에 더 가깝습니다.
imperative style, yes.
명령형 스타일입니다.
Okay, yeah, yeah, sure.
그래, 그래, 알았어.
I mean, it's easier to rate it, it is the advantage.
평가하기가 더 쉽다는 게 장점이지.
The effect is the same, but it is easier to rate.
효과는 같지만 평가하기가 더 쉽습니다.
Right, and so the question is, is the effect the same?
그래요, 그럼 문제는 효과는 동일하냐는 거죠?
Yes, but there's some cleanup situations
네, 하지만 몇 가지 정리 상황이 있습니다.
which are problematic with computable future.
계산 가능한 미래에 문제가 있습니다.
Sorry, there was a question here.
죄송합니다, 여기에 질문이 있습니다.
It's hard for me to actually see hands.
실제로 손이 잘 안 보여요.
Which exception did you get?
어떤 예외를 얻었나요?
Did you get the original exception
원래 예외를 얻었습니까?
or did you get the wrapped?
아니면 포장된 것을 얻었나요?
Okay, so the question is, is what exception
좋아, 그럼 문제는 어떤 예외가
is thrown here by throw of failed?
에 의해 여기에 던져지는 예외가 무엇일까요?
And in this particular method,
그리고 이 특정 메서드에서는
it's actually a wrapped exception.
실제로는 래핑된 예외입니다.
It's an execution exception
실행 예외입니다.
that actually wraps the original exception.
이 원래 예외를 실제로 감싸고 있습니다.
There's variations of this throw of failed,
이 실패의 변형이 있습니다,
which actually gives you the original exception,
실제로는 원래의 예외를 제공합니다,
allows you to map it.
를 매핑할 수 있습니다.
You can actually map it to itself if you want.
원한다면 실제로 자체에 매핑할 수 있습니다.
And so you have flexibility
따라서 유연성이 있습니다.
on how exceptions are propagated.
예외가 전파되는 방식에 대해 설명합니다.
Thank you.
고마워요.
There are a couple of instances you mentioned
언급하신 몇 가지 사례가 있습니다.
about the synchronized method of increment throw
증분 던지기의 동기화된 메서드에 대해
where the virtual thread gets the carrier thread.
여기서 가상 스레드가 캐리어 스레드를 가져옵니다.
There's also one more event
이벤트가 하나 더 있습니다.
which is capturing of the platform thread.
플랫폼 스레드 캡처입니다.
I know that for synchronized method,
동기화된 메소드의 경우
there is some work going on,
작업이 진행 중입니다,
so you don't have to worry about the synchronization method.
따라서 동기화 방법에 대해 걱정할 필요가 없습니다.
What is that one for, capturing?
저건 뭐야, 캡처?
Okay, so the question was,
좋아, 질문은,
is there's work going on in synchronized?
동기화에서 작업이 진행 중인가요?
Is there other work going on
다른 작업이 진행 중입니까?
around capturing a platform thread?
플랫폼 스레드 캡처와 관련된 다른 작업이 진행 중인가요?
Okay, I'm not quite sure what you mean by that.
무슨 뜻인지 잘 모르겠는데요.
I think we're out of time,
시간이 다 된 것 같아,
but if you come up, I'll deal with it here.
네가 올라오면 내가 여기서 처리할게.
Thank you.
고마워요.